Hey everyone and welcome. Have you ever wanted to talk about who's number one? You know,
みなさん、こんにちは。誰が一番か話したいことはありませんか？
the absolute best, the greatest? Well, today we're going to learn exactly how to crown a champion
絶対的な最高、最強のことです。今日は、チャンピオンをどうやって決めるか学びます。
in English. I mean, think about it, we're always ranking stuff, aren't we? Like, what's the biggest
考えてみてください。私たちは常に何かをランキングしていますよね？例えば、今一番人気のアニメは？
hit anime right now? Or who's the fastest runner in your whole school? To talk about stuff like
それとも、学校で一番速いランナーは誰か？そういうことを話すには、
that, to really declare a winner, you kind of need a secret code in English. And guess what?
英語で秘密のコードが必要です。そして、なんと、
Today, we're gonna crock that code together.
今日はそのコードを一緒に解き明かします。
All right, let's jump right into our first round.
さあ、最初のラウンドに飛び込みましょう。
I'm calling this the championship rule.
これをチャンピオンシップルールと呼びます。
This is the most important step for deciding
これは、誰が一番かを決めるための
who or what is the absolute best.
最も重要なステップです。
There's a secret formula and you're about to learn it. You ready?
秘密の公式があります。これから学びますよ。準備はいいですか？
Okay, so here it is, the secret formula.
では、これがその秘密の公式です。
For most short words that describe something,
短い言葉で何かを表す場合、
you know, like strong or fast, it's super simple.
例えば「強い」や「速い」など、すごく簡単です。
You just put the right in front and then you stick EST on the end.
「the」を前に置いて、最後に「EST」を付けるだけです。
So, the plus the word plus EST, that's it.
つまり、「the」＋単語＋「EST」、これだけです。
In grammar, this is called a superlative,
文法的には、これは最上級と呼ばれますが、
but let's just think of it as our number one word.
私たちはこれを一番の言葉と考えましょう。
Let's see it in action.
実際に見てみましょう。
All right, let's start with something we all know.
さあ、みんなが知っているものから始めましょう。
Mount Fuji is high, simple, right? Totally true, but is it just high
富士山は高い、シンプルですよね？本当にそうですが、ただ高いだけでしょうか？
or is it a true champion of height?
それとも、高さの真のチャンピオンでしょうか？
We can actually power up this sentence to show just how special it is.
この文をパワーアップさせて、どれだけ特別か示しましょう。
And boom, look at that. Mount Fuji is the highest in Japan.
ほら、見てください。富士山は日本で一番高いです。
By adding the and est, the sentence suddenly has way more punch, right?
「the」と「est」を加えることで、文が一気に力強くなりますよね？
It's not just a high mountain anymore.
もうただの高い山ではありません。
Now, it's the number one peak in all of Japan. It's the highest.
今や日本の一番の山、高さのチャンピオンです。
See how much cooler that sounds? Okay, you're getting it.
どれだけかっこいい響きになるか分かりますか？いい感じですね。
Let's do another one. How about this? The Nile River is long.
もう一つやってみましょう。ナイル川は長いです。
Yeah, it's a perfectly fine sentence,
そう、これは十分良い文ですが、
but fine is kind of boring, right? Let's make it a world champion.
「長い」というのはちょっと退屈ですよね？世界のチャンピオンにしましょう。
And just like that, bam, the Nile River
そして、ほら、ナイル川は世界で一番長いです。
is the longest in the world, see? We didn't just say it was long,
ただ「長い」と言ったのではなく、長さの無敵のチャンピオンにしました。
we made it the undisputed global champion of length
これも私たちのシンプルな公式で、
all with our simple little formula,
「the」＋「long」＋「est」、簡単ですよね？
the plus long plus est, easy, right?
さて、基本ルールは完全にマスターしましたね。
All right, so you've totally mastered the basic rule.
でも、本当のチャンピオンになるには、
But hey, to be a real champion,
いくつか特別な技が必要です。
you need a few special moves up your sleeve.
だから、スペルのパワーアップの時間です。
So it's time for some spelling power-ups.
これは、自分のルールで遊ぶ言葉のためのクールなトリックです。
These are some cool tricks for words
最初は本当に簡単なものです。「STIショートカット」と呼びましょう。
that, you know, like to play by their own rules.
では、もし単語がすでにEで終わっていたらどうしますか？
First up is a really easy one. Let's call it the STI shortcut.
この素晴らしいショートカットを使えます。
So, what do you do if a word already ends with the letter E?
例えば、「large」という単語を見てみましょう。すでにEで終わっていますよね？
Well, you get to use this awesome little shortcut.
だから、全体のSTをまた付ける必要はありません。それは無駄です。
Okay, so take a word like large. See how it already ends in E?
ただSTを付けるだけです。そうすると、largeはthe largestになります。
Well, you don't need to add the whole ST thing again. That'd be silly.
効率的なパワーアップで、ずっと早いです。
You just add ST, that's it. So large becomes the largest.
次のパワーアップは、YをIに変えるものです。
It's like an efficiency power-up, so much faster.
これはYで終わる単語、例えばbusyやhappyのためのものです。
Okay, power-up number two. I call this one the Y to I swap.
ここでのYは、まるで忍者のようです。
The Y here is kind of like a ninja.
まず、最後のYにさようならを言います。ポフ、消えました。
So here's how the magic trick works. Let's take busy.
そして最後に、チャンピオンシップの終わり、estを加えます。
First, you say goodbye to that Y at the end. Poof, it's gone.
アラカザム、busyはthe busiestに変身します。
Then in its place, an I shows up.
そして、最後のエキスパートレベルのパワーアップです。
that have a special pattern like big or hot.
特別なパターンを持つ言葉、例えば「大きい」や「熱い」。
To make them the champion, you gotta give them a little extra boost.
チャンピオンにするためには、少し特別な力を与えなきゃ。
So here's the deal. For a word like big, you can't just add EST.
だから、例えば「大きい」には、単にESTを付けるだけじゃダメ。
Nope, you have to double that last letter first. So big gets another G
そうじゃなくて、まず最後の文字を2倍にする必要がある。
and then it becomes the biggest.
「大きい」はGをもう一つ加えて、
It's like that extra letter gives it the superpower
「一番大きい」になる。
it needs to win the championship.
その追加の文字が、チャンピオンになるための力を与える。
Okay, you've learned the championship rule.
さて、チャンピオンシップのルールを学びましたね。
You've unlocked all the power-ups.
すべてのパワーアップを手に入れました。
Now it's time to put your new skills to the test.
さあ、新しいスキルを試す時です。
Welcome everyone to the final showdown. I'm gonna give you a sentence
皆さん、最終対決へようこそ。文を出しますので、
and you have to find the superlative. Are you ready? Let's do this.
その中の最上級を見つけてください。準備はいいですか？行きましょう。
All right, question number one.
では、質問1です。
My grandfather is the blank in my family and the word is old.
私の祖父は家族の中で一番の空白で、言葉は「古い」です。
This is just a little warm up. Pretty straightforward.
これはちょっとしたウォームアップ。簡単です。
Think you got it? And the answer is oldest. Yes, perfect.
わかりましたか？答えは「一番古い」です。はい、完璧です。
That's a textbook use of our main championship rule. Awesome start.
これは私たちの主要なチャンピオンシップルールの教科書的な使い方です。素晴らしいスタート。
Okay, on to the next one. Think a little harder on this one.
次の問題に行きましょう。少し考えてみてください。
Monday is the blank day at the store.
月曜日は店での空白の日です。
The word is busy. Hmm, which power up are you gonna need here?
言葉は「忙しい」。さて、どのパワーアップが必要ですか？
The answer is busiest, exactly right. You remembered the Y to I swap.
答えは「一番忙しい」、その通りです。YをIに変えるのを覚えていましたね。
You dropped that Y, swapped in the I and added S, nice.
Yを落としてIに変え、Sを加えました、素晴らしい。
If you got that one, you are totally getting the hang of this.
これができたなら、完全にコツをつかんでいます。
And here we go, the final question of the showdown.
さあ、最終問題に行きましょう。
The desert is the blank place on earth. Your word is hot.
砂漠は地球上での空白な場所です。言葉は「熱い」です。
Okay, this is the expert level test.
これは専門家レベルのテストです。
Remember that last power-up we learned?
最後のパワーアップを思い出して。
And the correct answer is, hottest, H-O-T- T-E-S-T.
正解は「一番熱い」、H-O-T-T-E-S-Tです。
Yes, you nailed it. You remembered to use the double up power up
はい、見事です。ダブルアップパワーアップを使うのを忘れませんでしたね。
to make that word a champion.
その言葉をチャンピオンにしました。
You've officially passed the final showdown, amazing.
あなたは正式に最終対決をクリアしました、素晴らしい。
You did it, seriously. You completed the whole challenge
やりました、本当に。全てのチャレンジを完了しました。
and you proved you know exactly how to talk about being number one.
そして、あなたは一番になることについて正確に話せることを証明しました。
I hereby declare you an official superlative champion.
ここに、あなたを公式な最上級チャンピオンと宣言します。
So let's do a super quick recap of the skills you just mastered.
では、あなたが習得したスキルを簡単に振り返りましょう。
First, the main championship rule, the plus your word plus S.
まず、主要なチャンピオンシップルール、あなたの言葉にSを加えること。
Then you unlocked three awesome power-ups,
次に、3つの素晴らしいパワーアップを手に入れました。
the S shortcut for words that end in E,
Eで終わる言葉のためのSショートカット、
the clever Y to I swap for words like busy,
「忙しい」のような言葉のためのYからIへの巧妙な変換、
and of course the powerful double up for words like big.
そしてもちろん、「大きい」のような言葉のための強力なダブルアップ。
You've got all the tools now. So you now have the secret code.
あなたはすべてのツールを手に入れました。これで秘密のコードを持っています。
You know how to talk about the best of the best,
最高のものについて話す方法を知っています。
the highest, the longest, the busiest, the hottest.
一番高い、一番長い、一番忙しい、一番熱い。
So I'm gonna leave you with one final question.
では、最後の質問をお送りします。
Now that you're a champion of superlatives,
今やあなたは最上級のチャンピオンです。
what's something that you are the best at? Think about it.
あなたが一番得意なことは何ですか？考えてみてください。
Thanks so much for hanging out with me today
今日は一緒にいてくれてありがとう。
and I'll catch you on the next one.
次回お会いしましょう。